And we'll
go ahead and call this meeting to order. This is the Board of Finance of the Town of Andover special meeting of Wednesday,
01/18/2023.
This is a special meeting with a very specific
agenda
item,
and as usual with any special meeting, we do not have the option to change
the agenda in any way. So we will go ahead and proceed for the agenda that was distributed.
First,
we'll go ahead and say the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of The United States Of America and to the Republic for which it stands one nation under God indivisible with liberty and justice for all.
You
okay I didn't agenda number item number two is public speak doesn't look like we have any members of the public on Eric
Eric Correct.
Eric Okay we'll move on to agenda item three which is the public works plow truck, this is the only agenda item we have
for this
subcategories
it purchase agreement financing method terms source of funding, and the Board of Selectmen's
referral.
Eric, do want to give us the overview and
talk about the purchase?
>> Sure.
So at this point,
you've all seen, I think, the
equipment plan for the town of Andover.
What we've been anticipating
is buying
a plow truck every five years,
because that seems to be the lowest overall
cost point for the town.
The range for municipalities,
some get rid of them
as soon as twelve years, others run seventeen to twenty years.
So, and for the record, state DOTs
by and large,
their
cycle for a truck of this size would be around eight years before they would get rid of it.
So, chose that point because
that means we have the primary trucks stay in service
for fifteen years,
and then they have five years as a reserve vehicle before we get rid of them.
So that's the basic plan.
Just to go through
the
numbers, essentially what the town has
settled on,
and this has been approved by both CAIP
and the Board of Selectmen
is buying
a truck off the state bid contract.
You know, which is a Freightliner vehicle,
Freightliner
chassis.
And the reason we're doing it now
is these have an eight to twelve month build time.
And right now it's at the shorter end of the time,
but if we don't order it fairly quickly, we're not going to have, right now it looks like we still have a build slot,
but we wait a couple of months and we're not going to have a build slot in this year,
And we would be anticipating a truck for
fall of twenty twenty four,
not fall of twenty twenty three.
So,
that's what the goal is
in terms of the purchase agreement
because
the
truck is beyond what we can afford to buy outright
with capital.
We are going to be essentially
taking a five year loan on the vehicle to be paid back over a total of five years.
But the finance company
is requiring
that we escrow the money now
as we sign the contract. So this, we will essentially be escrowing the money now and signing the contract,
even though we're looking at a delivery
in eight months best case scenario.
So that's where we're at with this.
You know, we always have the problem with these that
the trucks have to be purchased out of cycle, because if you wait until the budget is approved,
then you run into the case where
you get delivery of it two years down the road, not one year down the road.
That's kind of where we're at with this
truck.
So that's basically the finance or
the
contract.
Anybody have questions on that
I know Louise had some questions about
the.
The extended warranty
and that extended warranty and the details of that are baked into the price of this.
And given the cost of repairing,
you know, an engine failure or an engine issue,
I mean, we definitely think that's appropriate. So that's baked right into the cost
of the,
you know,
the vehicle.
We are also,
along with the state bid, we've spec ed the Tenco all season bodies.
The
reason we did that is because in the past, the town has always bought the least expensive mild steel bodies,
but we've pretty consistently
had to
replace bodies on the vehicles
at about the ten year mark.
And the
cost to do a body replacement on these vehicles has been running, was running about $40,000
I think it's more now. I think just the body itself without labor is over 40.
So, it's more economical to spend the money upfront
to get the stainless all season body with the hard ox floor than it is to get the mild steel ones, which we've done in the past.
And for the record,
our Ford
plow truck has been completely rebodied once,
and now is showing significant
signs of rust.
And our 2,004,
which is truck number seven,
we elected
not to buy the body because we just didn't have the money in the capital funds
the last couple years.
So we did a major welding repair on that one to try to get it through.
That was about $12
last year. We probably have to do the other side of that body because the other side's getting really funky too.
So we're going to end up spending on that one, you know, probably another 12,000 to $14,000
on the opposite side to fix that up. Because even though that's a 2,004,
and, you know, it's already, what, eighteen years,
we still have to limp that one. That will still one will still be limped along as our fourth spare vehicle for the next five years. So we are gonna have to spend the money to keep that in repair,
even though that's a pretty expensive vehicle to keep on the road right now. It will be less expensive when it's just a backup
and it's not in
daily use.
So
that is that.
Does anybody have questions
on
that?
Joanne?
You're on mute, so. Yeah,
>> thank you. Just, is this the typical way that this happens? I know you said
usually it comes up between budget season so you don't have to wait the two years for a new truck.
So
when
the time comes, is it usually like this we call a special meeting, you've always had it, it's never a planned expense, it kind of comes in the middle where we'll have to make a decision, call a town meeting. Is that what you've noticed?
>> So, the last time we did this
was in 2018,
and we had the town meeting in I think March
to order the last
unit,
which we got for the twenty nineteen-twenty
twenty
plow
season.
So yes,
yes, because it's off cycle, the last time we had enough money in the unexpended fund balance,
but we bought that one outright.
That one was about $193,000
This one's considerably more expensive,
even though we're actually
switching manufacturers,
because the Peterbilt trucks now spec'd the way we want them,
those were, you know, even
20 something thousand dollars more than this unit.
So international,
you know, we discard even though they're the lowest bidder
because those vehicles all seem to have a much lower life expectancy and a much higher cost of maintenance.
But the Freightliner chassis,
you know, in the last ten or twelve years have seemed to be very reliable. So, we feel like we can safely switch
to Freightliner
and it's lower cost. So, that's what we're anticipating doing.
Thank
you.
>> And the escrow amount just is based on the lowest of the payment
amounts and the financing options at the end of the
end of the proposed
contract?
>> Correct. That may change slightly
because this has already expired,
but the goal is before the town
meeting
to have the exact updated figure. So we can just make a motion. I don't think it's gonna change much.
The cost is not gonna change, but,
you know, there was
and I don't think there's been an interest rate adjustment, since this
quote was received in now,
but.
Because this quote is is expired will be expired by three weeks or so prior to the meeting, we will have to get an updated finance agreement.
So again, I don't think it's going to change it much, but it's possible it does.
I talked to the town's attorney and the town's attorney said you could either,
because it's a town meeting and the town meeting can change its mind,
you could change that number slightly by announcing a new figure at the meeting,
or just give yourself a little wiggle room and set it to 60,000
or such.
>> Well we would have to,
okay yes I mean we have to approve the whole thing right and that's necessarily just the 60,000 right?
>> Yes,
you would have so.
If we had enough money in the fund.
You as a board of selectmen,
since it's a budget, since the capital fund for public works equipment is budgeted,
you would not have had to go back to town meeting.
Where you're having to go down to town meeting
is only a town meeting can approve any indebtedness from the town.
So that automatically,
the fact that we're doing lease payments of this automatically makes this a town issue.
>> Yep.
Does anybody have any further questions for Eric?
Joanne?
>> I just have one more. I remember at one of the meetings, either our last meeting or the Board of Selectmen
when this went through,
because
it's held in escrow,
kind of like a down payment or an insurance plan sort of that we are going to go through and not pull out. Is that the first payment?
I forget how that stacked out how you talked about it deciding
where to take the money from there was discussion on that.
>> So we basically have to escrow and send them a check right now as soon as we sign this contract for
$58,888.95.
So, that will be gone out of our bank accounts as soon as this,
you know,
in held in escrow
until such time as we take delivery of the vehicle, and then that becomes the first payment.
Thank you. I just wanted clarity.
Thank you.
Yep.
>> And we've got to do that to get the process going and retain the build slot and get them working out. Right. Right. So.
I have a question.
Louise?
>> Yeah,
the reason for the, public hearing,
is it basically just to communicate this to the town?
Mean, do they have a,
Can they turn around and say no, we don't want this done? Absolutely.
Okay.
>> It's really a town meeting because because of like
Eric said, the in there going
into debt for multiple years, the crossing over multiple budget years hasn't been approved for all intents and purposes so.
>> Right.
Okay. So there will be other things on the on the meeting for approval,
because what none of us realized until we got into this and I had the town attorney look at this
is I have to also get my grant applications approved at town meeting,
which is
nuts, but any grant application
that requires a match on the town side technically has to get approved at town meeting.
We're going have a few of those up for discussion also.
>> So if we have one of these situations where it's an eightytwenty deal,
you know, the town's responsible for 20%, we can't just budget for that in a normal budget process. You have to go to the town for a special meeting? According to the charter, yeah. We have never done that. Wow. Right.
>> I know. The last time we did that was for Bunker Hill Bridge replacement,
and it got turned down flat by the town.
So it's it's scary. But, you know, it is town money, and that's they can do what they choose to do.
We appear we just lost Mark,
>> by the way. It does look like we did. We'll see if he comes back.
In the meantime, Eric, I ask you a quick question? When I the last CIP meeting,
this we talked about the truck a bit,
and I got really confused because of some of the comments that
Adrian made to you. You know, basically, it's in the budget. Go get it.
That doesn't seem to be correct.
>> Well,
so here's the issue.
Our charter
is fairly convoluted.
There are a bunch of things in there that
make it somewhat difficult to operate.
And
it's not in
the section that refers to this
is not at all in the finance section.
It's a couple of lines in the section that relates to special meetings.
It's like, by the way,
if you're taking on any indebtedness,
that takes a special meeting. Oh, by the way, if you're submitting any grant,
that requires a special meeting.
So we were looking through that in reference to something else.
You know, when I was talking to the town's attorney, I'm like, read that. Tell me if that thinks, if that says what I think that says it is, because that's not how we've been operating. So so that's kind of why we're going back and doing this.
You know?
Anybody know where the Gasco is?
Did Mark text anything?
You
>> want me to text him? I can try. Text him real quick and see where he went. Hey, Bill. Welcome.
>> Hey. Sorry. I'm late. My my company blocks Zoom from my computer, so
I had to do this long workaround.
It all deals to
Zoom from way back when they first started and they had those security breaches.
Sure. Anyways, it's a long workaround and I finally got it to work.
>> Okay. Fair enough. Okay. Alright, Rob. For some reason, Mark Brinker just dropped out of the Zoom call about two minutes ago, so we're just kinda waiting for Yeah. I'm assuming he's having technical difficulties. I just texted him to see what's going on.
>> Hey, Eric. Can I ask a follow-up question since you said
coming into temp meeting, how many of your grant applications are gonna have to go on? Is it
>> Anything to match? Is there any dollar amount? Yeah. Right now there's three Julian, I apologize. That's okay. There are three grant applications.
The first is the steep grant, which we've already gotten.
That's a $275,000
grant. It requires about a $75,000
grant. We'd already decided to take that money from the multi use building fund.
So that is fully funded.
>> The second one is I don't think I knew that we were taking it from the multi use that's
that's you know,
and thank you for I think my question was going to stem from I think it kind of is a good idea to go through that maybe not a meeting, but some when it's a big amount,
like Robert was alluding to. 78,000
is a lot, you know,
but it of course grants are always good for the town. I'm not opposed, but I mean there has to be a balance of,
you know,
5,000,
matching 5,000, but 78. So I'll let you continue with the amounts of the rest. I don't think they're as big as that one. Just real quick, guys. He's
>> gonna call in. He lost his Internet. Yeah. I'm back. Can you hear me? Oh, hey, Mark. We can hear you. Yeah. I'm on my phone. I'm not sure what happened. It looks like we lost Internet here.
>> Oh, bummer.
Don't have Fortunately, have my phone handy. Responding to anything, so probably wasn't a motorist hitting the pole. But Yeah.
We have power, so that's a good thing. Yeah. That's it. That is a good thing.
>> Yeah. Eric,
I have a question.
If by if by chance at the public meeting, they say no to that,
what's our To what?
To the the, truck.
Do we have another plan? We don't buy a truck. Okay.
>> I I mean, we don't.
You know, every town meeting is a crapshoot and,
you know, the town has made many decisions in the past
that aired on the side of frugality that, you know, unintendedly
cost to the town a lot more money in the long run.
You know, we choose to do, we're on a fifteen year plan
because that appears
to be the lowest cost to taxpayers
when you take in the cost of purchase
and total equipment maintenance.
I mean, that's why we're doing it. And, you know, like,
I mean, that international
pickup truck we have, the 2004,
the town has spent way over $100,000
in repair costs and maintenance costs on that vehicle
to this point.
You know, and that's
not going to go away because we're in the range where major things could go.
And this is kind of an aside, but we're actively considering keeping the 2007
or not the 2007,
the 1997
Ford
instead of the
international,
even though it's newer,
because the repair record for the international has been a lot worse than the older Ford
because the older was
pre all the pollution equipment for diesel vehicles,
then it's much simpler. It does not have any of the the electronics that are in modern vehicles.
So we haven't made that decision, but the town will consider that.
>> So will this be, excuse me, communicated
to everyone,
like in
a letter form prior to the
meeting, or is it gonna be discussed right at the public meeting?
>> It'll
be discussed at the public meeting. I was anticipating
I would do a quick PowerPoint
presentation
for each of the grants
and for the plow truck decision and just lay out the town's case of why we think this is
and what the impact is to the town.
>> Can
you just finish your I interrupted you too and then the follow-up. Just that this so the two other grants we know this deep and
then what were the two other ones?
>> I've heard the second one is called the trip grant, which is a brand new Department of Transportation grant,
stands for transportation
rural infrastructure program grant.
That will be We're going to ask for about $800,000
and use that money to reconstruct
a section of Hendy Road,
a section of Long Hill Road,
and Skinner because
those are the roads that have the biggest kind of structural problems
that need extensive drainage work right now.
And then our match for that would be how much? So our match for that is not set in stone right now because those are construction grants. They don't pay for the cost of, we're gonna need some preliminary engineering work and survey work
for both the drainage
and for some of the things we're going to do on that. So, would, my best guess right now is we're going to be into that for somewhere between 25,000
and $30,000
in design work.
But that money will just come from our road improvement fund that we fund every year as part of the budget process.
So, we're not asking for any kind of supplemental money to match.
We're just, we're looking at it as,
you know, if we get the grant, that's just more roadwork for the same amount of money we would be spending anyway.
Okay. And then the third one?
>> Sorry. The third one
is a recreational
trails grant funded through the DEEP.
And the goal is a safe
multi use, so pedestrian cycling, that kind of stuff, connection
between
the
town hall area and the rail trail,
because that was something that was identified in the plan conservation and development
as a significant.
Impediment to multimodal transportation
ultimately
it is my intention to
submit a what's called a lot sick grant
to fund the construction of the trail.
You know, because it's one of the few things
that we,
the town of Andover actually has that they could submit a lots of grant.
But what I wanna do is I wanna use this grant to get a lot of the planning
and some of the engineering out of the way,
because again, lots of grants don't pay for
the,
you know, the design and engineering costs, they pay for the construction costs.
>> Eric, I'm
a little concerned we're kind
of deviating from our agenda,
and given that it's a special meeting and stuff I just you know unless unless this is kind of pertinent I think we should probably limit the discussion.
No truck.
>> Yeah,
he had mentioned we're talking about it at the town meeting so that's Okay.
Yeah, so that's
>> how it kind of moved in. Yeah, thank you. Yeah, good.
Just moving back to the truck.
>> Okay, any other questions for Eric?
Okay, does anybody
want to make a motion that the Board of Finance
approve the
referral of the purchase of the public works plow truck to a
town meeting for the next step in the purchase?
>> Mark, before we do that, can we have a real quick conversation
about source of funding?
Yeah, sure. Okay.
>> So just so that you know,
we have a fair bit of money at the moment in the Public Works Capital Equipment Fund,
but we're going to. You
know, bunch of that money on the bobcat in the trailer.
So
we're looking at a difference
if once we complete that fund completely we're looking for a deep difference of about 17,500.
The Board of Selectmen
recommended
that
since the money is just being escrowed,
that it could be taken from
unexpended fund balance.
The town treasurer,
Cheryl,
told me that in her opinion,
that
would be a supplemental
appropriation,
and you can't just do that. You would have to make a motion
for a supplemental appropriation
for that amount.
The good news is that that amount is below the threshold,
which requires a town meeting,
which is another way of saying the Board of Finance
could make that decision
separately
from the town meeting.
Does not have to be part of the town meeting discussion,
as, as I understand.
That's all I wanted to say on that. Or you could elect to take it from, from the,
either the town aid road fund and then reimburse the town aid road fund later if you had money in the budget,
or you could make a determination
to
take it from contingency if you were comfortable doing that. So those are really the options.
The Board of Selectmen
recommended
the unexpended fund balance,
but ultimately that's a Board of Finance decision.
>> Yeah, thanks, Eric. That was there and I didn't really think about it in those terms for the motion, but
that is an important explanation too.
So that probably becomes part of the motion that we
would move that if the truck purchase were to be approved at town meeting that
we would transfer $17,500
difference required
from
either the unexpended fund balance or some other fund.
Sound accurate?
>> That is, but ultimately,
I think you guys should probably weigh in on where you want to take it from if you're going to make the motion.
Yep.
But that's just me.
>> Without the stuff in front of me here.
We don't have the fund balances on this document. So
>> So
what fund are you do you want to know about?
>> Well, you've listed,
I think,
probably the three funds that would make the most sense, unexploded fund balance, the
contingency
fund or Town Road maybe.
Right.
>> I mean, have no idea what we have in unexplained fund balance because we don't have an audit back yet.
So that one, I don't know.
Town Aid Road, we just got our
January allotment of $93,000
We had, after all was said and done about $40,000
in that account for that, but we still owe a contractor
somewhere around $14,000
out of that.
So there is Ballpark 26
Plus 93
in the Town Aid Road account.
The Road Improvement account has been drawn down to zero at
this point.
So those are the funds. An unexpended fund or the
contingency
fund, we have not spent any money out of the contingency fund.
>> What was the contingency fund this year? Is it like 75,000,
something like that? I can't remember. It was reduced to 50,000.
50,000?
Okay.
Yep. But
>> if you chose that I can tell you that,
you know, we've had very few significant
overexpenditures
this year,
barring any natural disaster.
I think our current budget
should hold for the year,
at least on expenses. I'm not prepared to talk about where we are on revenues.
Although taxation has been coming in normal,
you know, we're right on track with taxation.
Okay. But I don't know about a lot of the little fees like how much we've collected. I haven't really gone through yet and analyzed what we've actually collected from the town clerk's office,
you know, in the building department funds up to this point. So I don't have that midyear gauge yet.
>> So the contingency fund, if we were to hit that, so that would basically
leave us at about slightly over $32,000
in the contingency fund, assuming we haven't spent it elsewhere, don't think so.
And
we have remaining
about five months left in the a little over five months in the fiscal year.
Yeah.
>> But at this point, you don't aren't aware of anything we would need to go to the contingency fund for?
>> No,
no. I think,
so far we're in reasonable,
in reasonably good condition.
So far it has not been an excessive snow year.
So,
you know, one of the things we always worry about is busting our
snow plowing account,
which can add up really fast.
So far,
we're quite
a bit under for where we should be right now.
Salaries,
we seem to be in a really good position.
Part of it is we haven't had,
for much of the budget year, we haven't had a full time,
you know, associate finance person.
So, you know, we've saved somewhere around $18,000
so far just by, because we haven't filled that position yet.
So overall, I think we're in pretty good shape.
I'm not seeing any major
overages
that are affecting us at this point.
>> Anybody have any thoughts or questions for Eric on the funding?
>> Joanne has a reason. Yeah, thank you. So even if, you know, I'm sort of leaning towards a contingency fund based on everything you said
and then say we do have overages and other accounts
later in the year there's always possibilities of journal entries or transferring funds from other accounts like you mentioned that haven't been used, correct,
Into those lines at the end of the year in a cleanup kind of way?
>> Yes, I mean, we often at the end of the year will transfer money laterally between budgets
for anything we're over.
And then we will address
things that are.
You know if there are priorities or priority funds we have that for whatever reason
we feel we've under budgeted,
the Board of Finance has transferred money into those,
you know, like for the tree fund, for instance, because
we can always spend more money cutting trees,
you know, and we desperately need that. Sure.
>> No, just for the purpose of making this decision, I know. No, thank you. And I remember from last year, I was on the board last year too, at that time of year, but I just wanted to make sure. If we do touch contingency,
we end up using the rest of, there are other ways to fund those over dues.
So I'm in favor of
taking the 17.5.
I mean, I know other people have opinions, but that's where I stand
from that, from the contingency.
>> Anybody have any other thoughts about funding sources for the
required amount, 17,500?
I would tend to agree with Joanne about using the contingency funding,
not knowing what the unexpected fund balance
is, you know, we didn't have a lot of wiggle room in that account
without having an audit. That makes me a little concerned.
So, you know, I don't feel super strongly that way, but, I think it seems like we should be able to make that work.
Other comments?
Anybody care to make a motion?
>> I can make the motion. I just need a little help with Yes. It's pretty complex.
I'm sorry.
>> I was just saying I I could do it too, but I was gonna ask for some help with the boarding, but I'll let Joanne do it because she has more experience than me. I'll try. I mean, I'd like to make a motion that
we
send.
Approve to send to the town meeting.
>> Right. That we wanna move
the topic
of purchasing
this new plow truck
to town meeting
based on everything we talked about tonight
with the stipulation
of making up the difference or needing the down payment,
the funding source would come from.
Do I need to put that in, Mark?
Yeah. I don't have everything in front of me, so I'm just kinda
yeah. So we would
we would use,
you know, what was already, I think,
41,000 in the equipment fund. Right, Eric?
>> So, I I would say what you're going to do is you're going to take the majority, the $41,000
from the equipment fund and you're going to take the remaining money from?
>> Contingency.
From the contingent. I just wanted to make sure I'm reading it right. So we'll take the 41,000
from the equipment fund,
making up the difference of the $17.05
or thereabouts.
Or am I allowed to say that? Because we said we're gonna, you know, come to think of the balance from the contingency fund is probably the way to put it. Okay, I'm gonna, yes.
>> Would And I think we also
would probably wanna stipulate that, you know, plus or minus 10%
because as Eric noted, the
quote is
expired. Therefore we need to go out for quote and there could be a small differential in the amount, so we don't want to get locked into some technicality about the amount being different.
>> I have to say that, so plus or minus 10%,
you know, to make up the difference of the new quote and the Yeah, due to differences
>> in the quote, right. Okay, yeah.
So I'm going to restate that, try
anyway, so it's a it's a complex,
very complex
motion, but it so,
Joanne,
correct me if I've misstated this as you intended,
but so Joanne has moved that the Board of Finance
approve
the plow truck purchase
as quoted for $258,608
rounded
down, and
we
vote to recommend
we pass this on to the town meeting
with the funding sources being $41,000
out of the equipment fund and the balance out of the contingency fund
and at the same time allowing for a
10%
increase due to changes in the quote,
due to, expired quote,
I guess roughly. Does that sound about right?
>> Yes. Yeah, I don't think you even need to include 10,
but No.
Whatever
you think, right?
>> You know, it's going to be what it's going to be. Whatever we get the quote is going to go in front of the town meeting. Let's just leave ourselves open for that, right? If it's 10% higher, maybe they'll vote it down. It doesn't matter. We still have to go to town meeting.
So
that would be my thought.
I'll go ahead and second that.
Okay.
Thank you, Louise.
So much Further
>> discussion
on the motion?
Okay. Hearing none, will call for a vote. All those in favor, aye. Aye.
Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Okay, the motion passes unanimously.
Thank you everybody.
Thank you, Joanne, that was a tongue twister even
being happy to be restated two or three times. I'll just study on that.
Okay,
so,
again, we do not appear to have anybody
in the public here, although we don't actually have another public speak item on there.
We'll go directly to adjournment.
Anybody would like to make a motion to adjourn?
I'll make the motion to adjourn.
>> Okay, thank you, Bill. Do I have a second?
I'll second it. Thank you, Louise. Any discussion?
All those in favor say aye.
Aye.
Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Hearing none, the motion is adjourned or the meeting is adjourned.
Thank you.